[Music]
hello and welcome to today's video
today's video is just going to be a
little quick uh video
hopefully quick uh showing how we can
set up this
hotbar system
to be able to choose a slot and then for
example if we uh left click we can use
whatever
item that we've currently got
highlighted on our hotbar if i left
click you can see down in the console
we're saying using health potion
but using cog using poison potion and
using sword item you see with the scroll
wheel i can scroll kind of just
infinitely through all of these slots
and then i can also select individual
slots with the number
row on the keyboard so this isn't going
to be a line by line tutorial like kind
of follow along project files are
available obviously to download on the
patreon
account if you do want to download the
code and just plug it straight into your
inventory system uh you can obviously do
that by downloading the patreon files if
this video ever ends up on youtube
because it's originally going to be a
patreon exclusive the url for the
patreon is linked in the description
below if you're watching this on youtube
kind of in the future if i release this
uh sort of down the line um but what i
will be doing is i'll be walking through
exactly what i've done and i'll be
showing the code on screen and obviously
feel free to pause and kind of copy it
down if you want to do that well like i
said just download the project files so
let's just jump straight into it there's
only going to be a couple of changes
really to get this to work so
i've made a hotbar display script so if
we open up this i'll go through this
kind of line by line you can see there's
a lot of just euler plate code which i
thought would be quite boring to just
type it out line by line so we've got
our hotbar display class which inherits
from our static inventory display
previously our hotbar was just a static
inventory display which is this class
here that we set up
way back when when we did the ui or the
inventory system and that itself
inherits from inventory display but we
don't need to worry about this class
we're not going to do anything there and
all we're going to do on this class is
we're going to swap our inventory slot
ui variables over to protected instead
of private so we can access it from our
hotbar display class we're going to make
sure our on enable and on disable our
protected virtual voids instead of
private voids and that's it for the
static inventory display class we're not
going to
change any of the other functionality
it's just making that protected and
making these two protected virtual voids
so if we now make a hotbar display
script and have this inherit from our
static inventory display class here
we're going to keep track of which slot
on our hotbar we've got selected and
this is going to be done
via a int an index and i've set this as
a private int we've got a max index size
which i defaulted to 9 but we are
setting it to the slots.length minus one
because obviously arrays are zero based
so if you've got ten inventory slots
and you want to access the tenth slot
we would actually want to be at index
nine to access that in the array and
then this is a little bit butchered um
over on our player movement code you can
see here that we've got private player
controls and we're making some new
player controls and that's how we move
our little bean around without getting
too bogged down so we need some input on
our hotbar display script you can see
we've got some copied code here we've
got private player controls player
controls equals new player controls and
what you'd probably want to do is not do
it this way and have instead a separate
input manager script but again that's
his own separate video i'm just trying
to do this the easiest way to show you
the logic of this hotbar display script
just like our player movement code where
we're setting up new controls so we can
access those controls we're doing the
exact same thing here so we're making
some new player controls in our
protected override void on enable and
protected override void on disable we'll
call in our base dot on enable
which is just going to
do this and then we're going to do our
own stuff so we're going to enable the
player controls and then in our on
disable we are just going to disable
them this just avoids any memory leaks
now we see this big kind of uh
subscription to all of these events and
then we're unsubscribing from them here
so the way i've set up these input
controls you see we've got hotbar one
hotbar two through to ten and then we've
got use item
as well and then we've also got a mouse
wheel input here i go back over to unity
go over to our input control so here's
our player input controls using the new
input system up until now we've only had
movement because we've just been moving
the bean around we haven't really we
haven't needed any of the controls you
can see here i've got hot bar one
through to ten plus mouse wheel plus
item so one through ten these are all of
the same so it's just a action type of
pass-through and it's a button
and one on the keyboard i've got an
interaction of press only
and then i've done this on every single
one it's the exact same so hotbar two is
number two on the keyboard with an
interaction of press only you can see
all the way to 10 and 10 is actually
zero on the sort of row of number keys
on your keyboard obviously that's slot
10 which is
after nine that's zero on the keyboard
we have mouse wheel which is passed
through an axis
and i've chosen for the path mouse
scroll y
and then use item
again is a button or the left mouse
button and there's an interaction of
press only there as well so this is how
you need to set up your input action
asset with a key for every single row on
the keyboard the numbers from one to ten
or one to zero mouse wheel and use item
and with that done we can go into our
script and then we're just listening out
for when the player presses a button so
we've got hotbar one dot performed plus
equals and then a method called hotbar
one which just takes in an input
action.callback context called obj um
i've done that through one through ten
and then i've made um a method called
use item as well i'm unsubscribing from
them here and you see that we've got hot
bar one and then we've got a set index
method which takes in an int which i'll
show you in just a second
we've got set index in zero one two
three four five
and the reason these are offsets so
we're pressing number one on the
keyboard and again the array is zero
based so if we press one on the keyboard
we want to access the first
slot in our slots array
which is index zero because of it
because of their
because they're zero based so it's a
little bit you know annoying that that's
the case so we're setting when we press
one on the keyboard we're gonna set our
index to zero to access the first
element in our slots array and we do
that through hotbar one two three four
five six seven eight nine ten and
obviously when we press zero on the
keyboard we actually want to set it to
index nine and i've just wrapped these
in a region just so i can collapse them
because they're kind of
messy to look at in our update function
i've got if
playercontrols.player.mouseworld
float is greater than 0.1 then obviously
we've scrolled the wheel up during that
frame so we're going to choose the so
we're going to change the index and
we're just going to knock the index up
one and similarly if it's less than
minus 0.1 we're going to knock it down
and you can see here that i've got
private void use item so again we're
listening out for the left mouse button
when that's performed we're going to
call our use item method we'll do
private void use item we're going to say
if there is item data in the slot that
we have selected so if that item
that slot actually has an item in it
then we're going to call the use item
method over on our item data i'm going
to jump quickly over to the
inventoryitem.cs script and i've just
added a public void use item and that's
just going to debug.log our display name
and on your game you're going to do
different things based on which item is
selected so you may have use item and
then if you've got a weapon you may want
to make a new scriptable object that
inherits from inventory item data and
that's the weapon class and then use
item called some weapon logic if you'd
like to see that kind of set up let me
know and i'll do a follow-up video for
that i wanted to keep this video just
about the actual hotbar display to keep
it short and sweet so then we've just
got our actual index handling um code so
we've got change index which takes in a
direction to change it so
are we changing it up or we're changing
it down and again we're calling that
here in our update function based on
which way we're scrolling the mouse
wheel and here we're going to toggle the
slot uis highlight which i'll show you
in a second and then to our index we're
just gonna add the direction so for
index three and we go up one that'll
obviously change current index to four
and if we're index three and we go down
minus one obviously that'll put the
current index to two so once we've
changed the current index we need to we
need it to wrap around if it goes over
the max index size so we've worked at
index nine and then we go up to index 10
and our maximum index size is nine
then we're going to loop it back around
we're going to set the current index
back to zero and the sort of inverse of
that is if we're already at index zero
and we try to scroll the mouse wheel
down we go below zero then we're going
to set the current index back to our max
index size so it'll loop back around to
the top and then we can carry on
scrolling down minus in one until we're
back to below zero and then we're going
to call this toggle highlight code again
which again i'll show you and then set
index is pretty simple we're just
directly setting the index um to you
know whichever key we've pressed on the
keyboard i do have some sort of
validation stuff here
and
again just doing that wrap around
functionality we should never need to
use it because we
are setting it directly
but just for example if you
set a stacked
if you want a hot bar of size
five instead of using the full number
keys and you've forgotten to
um change this and like remove the the
keys this is just a good way of making
sure that we're safe that it will always
um display the correct sort of
index so if our max index size is five
and i press zero on the number pad i'm
just gonna set it to the max index size
and i'll just make sure we don't get any
errors you may wanna debug.log something
there as well just so you know that
you've come kind of out of bounds when
you've pressed the key
and then we're going to set our current
index to our new index then we're going
to call this toggle highlight
functionality and the reason we're
calling this twice here is because we're
going to toggle it so we're going to
turn it off for the slot we're currently
on then we're going to change the index
and then we're going to toggle that new
index on so if we just click through to
our toggle highlight script this is on
our inventory slot ui script and we've
got a public voice toggle highlight and
it's just going to set our slots
highlight to the inverse of itself so
we'll toggle it on or off this just
saves having to have a toggle highlight
on and a toggle highlight off uh method
you can see up here we've got a
serialized field uh private game object
slot highlight so we're just setting
that active so we're just turning that
on or off and by calling set active here
then if we go over to our slot inventory
slot ui prefab you can see here we've
got i added a new image
which i've turned off
in the inspector we need to remember to
turn that off
um and all this is is it's an image i've
made in photoshop it's just a square uh
you know square sort of highlight which
i've made it white in photoshop so i can
change the color of the highlight here
maybe we want it to be sort of a nice
kind of green color and i'll keep it
kind of yellowy orange and then i've
dragged that image over into our slot
highlight um on the prefab script if we
look at our canvas you can see we've got
our highlights here
and again i need to remember to turn our
image off so they are all off and then
one last thing in our hotbar display
class over in our protected override
start so here over here we've got
protected virtual void start and this is
uh this calls refresh static display on
display we're just overriding start we
are refreshing the display by calling
based on start we're going to set the
current index to zero we're going to set
our maximum index size to slot start
length minus one and then we're going to
toggle the highlight of slot zero on so
we press play there you go we can see
we've got that if i click in the slots
empty nothing happens you can see
nothing's happening in the console but
then if i pick up some stuff we've got
our cog
we've got our potions using health
potion and then we're using our sword so
there we have it that's how we can set
up a little hot bar selection obviously
there is more that we can do with this
um depending on your game so for example
when we change index we might want to
instantiate the sword for the player to
be holding it and then if we scroll off
it it will disable the sword um
you know we might want to show a potion
in the player's hands again using sort
of events like we've used events all
throughout this project you know you
could call an event that says slot
changed and it passes through the item
that is in that slot and then you can do
logic with
and then wherever you want and whatever
your game calls for you can do logic
with that this was a quick sort of fly
through again this was filmed as a
patreon exclusive if you're watching
this on youtube project files for this
are over on patreon which is
patreon.compass
if you've got any questions let me know
in the comments or join the discord
server um i'll be able to help you kind
of debug anything that's gone wrong but
in the meantime thanks for watching and
i'll see you the next one bye
you